<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaration of the Convention of Estates of the Kingdom of Scotland concerning the present expedition into England, according to the commission and order given from their meeting at Edenburgh, August 1643.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05243</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1216A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R187402</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51784653</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51784653</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175050</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05243)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175050)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2710:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaration of the Convention of Estates of the Kingdom of Scotland concerning the present expedition into England, according to the commission and order given from their meeting at Edenburgh, August 1643.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175050:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175050:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DECLARATION OF THE Convention of Eſtates OF THE KINGDOME OF SCOTLAND: CONCERNING The preſent expedition into <hi>England,</hi> according to the Commiſſion and Order given from their Meeting at <hi>Edenburg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Auguſt,</hi> 1643.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. W.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:175050:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175050:2"/>
            <head>THE DECLARATION Of the Convention of Eſtates of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now, wee ſuppoſe, knowne to the Chriſtian world, and will be knowne to after ages, what have beene the dangers and diſtreſſes of this Kirke and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in their Religion and Liberties; What their endeavours and wreſtlings have been for deliverance, and how mercifully and marvellouſly the good hand of God did ſettle their Religion and Peace, againſt the devices, attempts and practices of Papiſts, Prelates and Malignants: who, had they not been given up to incurable blindneſſe and hardneſſe of heart, would have ſeene and acknowledged the hand of God working againſt them, and themſelves fighting againſt God. But theſe Enemies of all righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, full of all ſubtilty and miſchiefe, do not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175050:3"/>ceaſe to pervert the right wayes of the Lord. Their great project and maine deſigne againſt the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion and people of God, is not altered, but continueth one and the ſame: their furie and malice is not abated, and their plots and policies deeper, and more wicked then before; onely finding their fraud fruſtrated, and their forces beaten back upon one ſide; they have with new ſtratagems, freſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and greater power, aſſaulted another part of the wall, and have made the breach ſo wide and large, that they have entred, and begun to roare in the midſt of the Congregations of Gods people, and ore ſetting up their Enſignes for Signes, which to the unſpeakable griefe of all who are not both voyd of Grace, and deprived of naturall affection, is to beſden this day in miſerable <hi>Ireland,</hi> and diſtreſſed <hi>England,</hi> and, unleſſe it be prevented by their timeous and ſpeedy deliverance, ſhall (wee know not how ſoon) be ſeen and felt in this Kingdome; where, as the enemies did begin, ſo ſhall they end this bloody, barbarous, and Anti-chriſtian tragedie, if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors be not interrupted and driven from the Stage, before they bring it to their intended concluſion and helliſh applauſe.</p>
            <p>It is wee confeſſe, no ſmall comfort to this Kirke and Kingdome, that we have been willing and ready by all good meanes from the beginning, to quench
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175050:3"/>this unnaturall fire; all who have had place and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like intereſt, the Lords of his Majeſties privie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, the Commiſſioners for conſerving the peace, and the generall Aſſembly of this Kirke and their Commiſſioners, having with all care and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe applied themſelves, from time to time, to uſe al good meanes; ſuch as are their humble deſires, their ſupplications, Declarations and Remonſtrances to his Majeſty for a bleſſed Pacification: And after all theſe had proved ineffectuall, Commiſſioners were ſent to repreſent how much this Kirke and Kingdome from their intereſt in the preſervation of their owne Religion, the ſafety of his Majeſties Perſon, and their neer relation to their Brethren of <hi>England,</hi> were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the unhappy differences, betwixt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and the houſes of Parliament, and in all humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and tenderneſſe, to make offer of their mediation and national interceſſion, for removing them in ſuch a way as might moſt ſerve for his Majeſties honour, and the good of his people; but after long atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, much contrary to their deſires and hopes, and to the expectation of al his Majeſties good Subjects in both Kingdomes (ſo prevalent were the Counſels of the Popiſh Prelaticall, and Malignant party, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending their owne troubles and miſery, in the publike peace and happineſſe of the King and his people) the offer of their humble ſervice and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175050:4"/>indeavours, was utterly refuſed &amp; rejected, upon no other reaſon, but that they had no warrant nor capacity for ſuch a mediation, although authorized by a Commiſſion from his Majeſty and Parliament for that effect; and that the intermixture of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church of <hi>England</hi> with the civill government, was ſuch a myſterie as could not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by them; although it be true which was then often replyed; that in the eighth demand of the Treaty of Peace, the deſire of uniformity in Kirke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government was kindly entertained, and received ſuch an anſwer, as hath been ſince a doore of hope to this Kirke and Kingdome of obtaining their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: and although the houſes of Parliament, who are beſt acquainted with the conſtitution of that kingdome, and whom it moſt concerneth, have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their Bill, for aboliſhing of Epiſcopall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not only as a great impediment to the perfect reformation and growth of Religion (which in a Chriſtian kingdome is a ſufficient ground) but alſo, as very prejudiciall to the civil ſtate &amp; government.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners having returned from <hi>Oxford</hi> without ſucceſſe, and the miſeries of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the troubles of <hi>England,</hi> and the dangers and preſſures of this kingdome more and more increaſing; the Lords of his Majeſties Councell, the Commiſſioners for conſerving the Peace, and the Commiſſioners for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175050:4"/>the Common burthens, all intruſted with the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like affaires of the kingdome reſpectively, found themſelves preſſed above their place and power, with difficulties, which required the Common Counſell, conſent and reſolution of the Eſtates of the kingdome, and were neceſſitate according to the practice of former times (his Majeſty having denied a Parliament, being ſupplicated for that effect) to call a Convention of the Eſtates, that by their wiſdome they might conſider of the common duty, and provide for the publique ſafety of the Kingdome, in a time of ſuch extremity. No ſooner did the Convention of Eſtates, which was met with more then ordinary frequency and alacrity, enter into publike conſultation, but the good providence of God ſtill watching over this Countrey for good, did bring to their hand, a diſcovery of divers trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous attempts, againſt the Kirke and Kingdom; as if the Convention had been called to receive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the dangers, and to provide remedies, for the ſafety of the publique. Like as the dangers diſcovered unto them, were made publikely known and with the advice of the Commſſioners of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly, the remedies alſo were agreed upon and publiſhed in print.</p>
            <p>Amongſt theſe remedies a chiefe one was, to conſider of the renewing of a league and aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175050:5"/>with <hi>England,</hi> for defence of Religion, and the mutuall peace of the Kingdomes againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy, and how farre the ſame might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended againſt Prelacie and popiſh Ceremonies for uniformity in Kirk-government, and the externall worſhip of God, as is more fully expreſſed in the Remonſtrance of the remedies of the dangers of Religion. But before the Convention of Eſtates had entered upon this grave conſideration Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners came from both Houſes of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> warranted and authorized to propound their deſires of the ſame union &amp; ſtrait conjunction of the two Nations, againſt Papiſts, and Prelates, with their adherents; And to conſider with the Eſtates of this Kingdome, of ſuch articles or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, as might make the aſſiſtance and union betwixt the two Nations more beneficiall and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall for the common ſecurity of Religion and Liberty. Upon the manifeſtation of this concurſe of the ſtrong inclinations and deſires of the Eſtates of both Kingdomes, with which the Generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, did moſt unanimouſly and heartily joyne their deſires, counſels, and prayers, a Committee of the Convention of Eſtates, and a Committee of the Generall Aſſembly, were appointed to meet, with the Commiſſioners of the Houſes of Parliament, for conſidering the beſt and readieſt waies, by which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175050:5"/>theſe common deſires and conceptions might be ripened and brought forward toward perfection, and (if it were poſſible) to birth and action, for the comfort of both Kingdomes, in Religion and peace. Theſe three Committees after ſome meetings for debate and deliberation, did reſolve in end, that, according to the commendable practice of the two Kingdomes in former times of diſtreſſe and danger, the example of the people of God in other Nations, in the like caſe; and the late example of the Kirke and Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the beſt and moſt effectuall meanes for preſerving Religion, and both kingdomes from utter ruine and deſtruction, and for procuring peace, and all other bleſſings, were: That both kingdomes enter into a ſolemne League and Covenant to be ſworne and ſubſcribed by His Majeſties Subjects of all degrees in both kingdomes, who love the true Proteſtant, reformed Religion, His Majeſties honour and ſafety, and their owne happineſſe: And therefore they did with common conſent agree upon the firſt lineaments and principall parts of a Covenant, to be offered to the view, and to be conſidered by the wiſedome of the full Aſſembly of the kirke, and Convention of Eſtates, which, how ſoone it was preſented unto them, and read once and againe in their audience, did ſo affect their hearts, that the fire which had made them to melt in teares at the ſolemnizing of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175050:6"/>the Nationall Covenant of this kingdome, did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to burn againe, and bring forth the ſparkles of the like affection; and withall did fill them with confidence and hope, that the Lord, inclining the hearts, of the Houſes of Parliament, and of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and wel-affected people of <hi>England,</hi> to joyn in this Covenant, they wil thereby find an anſwer from Haaven to all the prayers, which they have offered up with ſtrong crying and teares a deliverance from all their ſufferings and feares, and the beginning of a new World of joy and peace, which the Lord will create for their comfort.</p>
            <p>But we know on the other part, upon the ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and ſubſcribing of this Covenant by true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Patriots, the oppoſite and malignant party of Papiſts, Prelates, and others the ſonnes of defection and contention their adherents, will rage and tumultuate more then ever before. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, unleſſe we will either betray our Religion, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and Lawes, and all that we and ours doe poſſeſſe, into their hands and ſuffer our ſelves to be cut off and maſſacred by ſuch bloody and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous cruelty, as they have executed this time paſt in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> there is a neceſſity of taking of Armes for mutuall defence, in the cauſe of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of the Kings honour, of the liberty and peace of the kingdomes, and of every one of us in our own private eſtate and condition. In this caſe it is moſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175050:6"/>neceſſary, that every one againſt all doubting be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in his minde of the lawfulneſſe of his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, and of the goodneſſe of the Cauſe maintained by him, which is no other, then the good of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>England,</hi> and the deliverance of our Brethren out of the depths of affliction, the preſervation of our owne Religion, and of our ſelves from the extremity of miſery, and the ſafety of our native King, and his kingdomes from deſtruction and deſolation: Any one of which, by all Law divine and humane, is too juſt cauſe of taking of armes, how much more when all of them are joyned in one? Whoſoever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draweth and hideth himſelf in ſuch a debate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, let him conſider, whether he be not a hater of his Brethren againſt Chriſtian and common chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; an hater of himſelfe and his poſterity againſt the law and light of nature; A hater of the King and his kingdomes, againſt loyalty and common duty; And a hater of God againſtall Religion and Peace.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt, The queſtion is not, nor need we diſpute, whether we may propagate our Religion by Armes, but whether, according to our power wee ought to aſſiſt our Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> who are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for our help, and are ſhedding their blood in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of that power, without which, Religion can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be defended nor reformed, nor unity of Religion with us, and other reformed Kirks be attained: who have in the cauſe of Religion, and the like exigence
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175050:7"/>aſſiſted us and other reformed Kirks: to whom, of old and of late, we have made promiſes of the reall Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of all Chriſtian duty and thankfulneſſe; And who, upon our deſires and their indeavours for unity in Religion, have often warned us, that the malignant party would bend all their invention and forces to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt the work, and to ruine &amp; deſtroy them in the undertaking of it, which we ſee this day come to paſſe. The queſtion is no ſooner rightly ſtated, but it is as ſoone reſolved: the Lord ſave us from the curſe of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roz, who came not to help the Lord, to help the Lord againſt the mighty:</hi> when we look upon the Cauſe which they maintaine, the prayers, teares, and blood which they have powred forth, and the inſolencies and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the enemies, we cannot doubt, but inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and deliverance ſhall ariſe unto <hi>England;</hi> but we have reaſon to feare, if we upon ſo faire a calling, ſit ſtill and hold our peace, this kirke and kingdome ſhall periſh by the hand of the ſame enemy, and there ſhall be none to deliver us: And who knowes, whether the Lord hath granted us mercy, furniſhed us with men of war, put weapons in our hands; and called this great Councel of the Eſtates, for warrant &amp; direction for ſuch a time as this? God forbid, and be it far from us to ſit downe at eaſe (if wee may promiſe to our ſelves eaſe) on this ſide of <hi>Jordan,</hi> till our Brethren be poſſeſſed in the liberties of the kingdome of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Neither concerning the ſecond, is the queſtion (as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175050:7"/>our enemies would make it) whether wee ſhall enter into <hi>England,</hi> and lift armes againſt our owne King, who hath promiſed and done as much as may ſecure us in our Religion and Liberties; but whether againſt the Popiſh, Prelaticall, and malignant party their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, prevailing in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> wee be not bound to provide for our owne preſervation. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it had not beene often told us from <hi>England,</hi> and the reformed kirks in other places, wee might of our ſelves have knowne from our continuall experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ever ſince the time of our firſt reformation, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after the two kingdomes have been united un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one Head and Monarch, from the Principles of our own Declarations, in the time of our late troubles and dangers, from the vindictive diſpoſition of the enemies of this kirke and kingdom (which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be the fountaine whence have iſſued all theſe evils) and from the grounds of common reaſon, That we cannot long like <hi>Goſhen,</hi> enjoy our light, if darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall cover the face of other reformed kirks? that <hi>Juda</hi> cannot long continue in liberty, if <hi>Iſrael</hi> be led away in captivity, and that the condition of the one kirke and kingdome, whether in Religion or Peace, muſt be common to both? If <hi>England</hi> ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the enemies of Religion without that aſſiſtance which they call for from us at this time, what help can we expect from them in the houre of our tentation, which we have deſerved, and the Lord may bring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175050:8"/>us when he will. God forbid, that we ſhould give them cauſe to laugh at our calamity, and mock when our feare commeth; and if they ſhall be given over in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hand of the Enemy (which God in his mercy avert) will not the enemy ſtrengthened with increaſe of power, be the more inſolent and unreſiſtable, and will not the power of <hi>England,</hi> turned into the hands of Malignants, turne alſo enemy againſt this Kinke and kingdome, and upon ſuch pretences as be already invented, and yet (they will alledge) according to the late. Treaty of peace, within three Moneths ſpace, denounce a nationall war againſt us.</p>
            <p>And concerning the third the queſtion is not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ſhould preſume to be Arbitrators in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters now debated by fire and ſword; betwixt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and the houſes of Parliament which may ſeeme to be forraigne and extrincecall to this Nation, and wherein we may be conceived to have no intereſt, but whether our mediation and interceſſion being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by the one ſide, upon hope of victory; or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, by both ſides, upon confidence of their owne ſtrength, and ſeverall ſucceſſes, it be not our duty, it being in our power, to ſtop or prevent the effuſion of Chriſtian blood? Or whether we ought not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to reſcue Our Native King, his Crowne and Poſterity out of the midſt of ſo many dangers, and to preſerve his people and kingdome from ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction? If every private man be bound in duty to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175050:8"/>interpoſe himſelfe as a reconciler and ſequeſtrator betwixt his neighbours, armed to their mutuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction? if the ſonne ought to hazard his owne life for the preſervation of his Father and brother at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance the one againſt another? Shall a kingdome ſit ſtill and ſuffer then king and neighbouring kingdome to periſh in an unnaturall war. In the time of animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and appetire of revenge, ſuch an interpoſing may be an irritation: But afterwards, when the eyes of the mind no more blood-run with paſſion, doe diſcerne things aright, it ſhall be no grief, nor offence of heart, but matter of thankſgiving to God, and to the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which have kept from ſhedding of blood, and from revenge.</p>
            <p>The Covenant is now ſolemnly taken in <hi>England,</hi> and is countenanced there already from heaven with marvellous ſucceſſe. The Propoſitions and Articles of the Treaty are with wonderfull unanimity conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in both houſes of Parliament, ceſſation of armes is agreed upon with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, and they, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the barbarous and unparalleld cruelty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed by the upon the Proteſtants &amp; people of God in that kingdome, honoured with the title of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Subjects; It is therefore now high time for all true hearted Scottiſh men and good Patriots abroad, eſpecially ſuch as upon faire and plauſible pretences have been formerly miſtaken or ſeduced to take arms againſt this Cauſe of God and Religion, timely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175050:9"/>their nationall Covenant, and ſeriouſly to bethink themſelves of the duty, which by ſo manifold Obligation they owe to their Religion and native Countrey in this time of ſo great diſtreſſe and danger to both; leſt, deſpiſing or neglecting this our warning and intimation, they either periſh by wilfull perſiſting in their own wayes againſt God, their Countrey, and Covenant; or come too late, &amp; there be no place left for repentance. It is alſo moſt neceſſary for all the good people of all ranks and degrees within the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to deny themſelves and their own eaſe, or what earthly thing is deareſt unto them, to lift up their eyes and behold the worke of God unto which they are called; and with heart &amp; hand to joyn in this ſo reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, ſo juſt, and ſo neceſſary expedition, and which upon the truth of God, our own late comfortable and never to be forgotten experience, and the prayers of the people of God, we may be aſſured, will, in end, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all difficulties and oppoſition, be crowned with ſuch ſucceſſe, as may be honour to God, confuſion to his preſumptuous and incorrigible enemies, propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the true Religion, and comfort to all the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned lovers of truth and peace, which againſt all calumny and contradiction hath been, is, and ſhall be the ſumme of our deſires.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:175050:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
